<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc autobreaks="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    <!ENTITY rfc6333 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6333.xml">
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-softwire-map SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-map.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-softwire-lw4over6 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-lw4over6.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.stenberg-homenet-hncp SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.stenberg-homenet-hncp.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5340 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5340.xml">
    <!ENTITY rfc2328 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml">
    <!ENTITY rfc6334 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6334.xml">
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-softwire-map-dhcp SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-map-dhcp.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dhc-dhcpv4-over-dhcpv6 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-dhcpv4-over-dhcpv6.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-liu-homenet-softwire-00" ipr="trust200902">

<front>
  <title abbrev="Softwire in Homenet">Building Softwire in IPv6 Home Network</title>

  <author fullname="Yong Cui" initials="Y." surname="Cui">
    <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Department of Computer Science, Tsinghua University</street>
      <city>Beijing</city>
      <code>100084</code>
      <country>P.R.China</country>
    </postal>
    <phone>+86-10-62603059</phone>
    <email>yong@csnet1.cs.tsinghua.edu.cn</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author fullname="Cong Liu" initials="C." surname="Liu">
    <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Department of Computer Science, Tsinghua University</street>
      <city>Beijing</city>
      <code>100084</code>
      <country>P.R.China</country>
    </postal>
    <phone>+86-10-6278-5822</phone>
    <email>gnocuil@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
    
  <date year="2014"/>
  
  <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

  <abstract>
    <t>In IPv6 home network, IPv4 service may still be needed for a long time.
    	 ISP can provider IPv4 service through IPv4-over-IPv6 softwire mechanisms,
    	 e.g. Dual-Stack Lite (<xref target="RFC6333"/>). This document discusses
    	 how to build softwires from home routers, especially when there are multiple
    	 routers those are running distributed configuration and routing protocols.
    </t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In IPv6 home network environments, when there are multiple routers,
      	 the routers are running distributed configuration and routing protocols.
      	 HNCP (<xref target="I-D.stenberg-homenet-hncp"/>) is designed to configure
      	 home routers with IP prefixes and other information including stateless DHCPv6 options
      	 provided by ISPs. OSPFv3 (<xref target="RFC5340"/>) is used for IPv6 routing
      </t>
      
      <t>As the IPv6 transition takes a long time and large cost, the demand of IPv4 service
      	 may still last for a long time and the ISP still needs to provide IPv4 service. To deal with
      	 the shortage of IPv4 addresses, several IPv4-over-IPv6 softwire mechanisms are proposed,
      	 e.g. Dual-Stack Lite (<xref target="RFC6333"/>), MAP (<xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"/>), and Lightweight 4over6 (<xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-lw4over6"/>).
      	 The three mechanisms are similar in many aspects: provisioning specific information by DHCPv6, and
      	 IPv4 packets are transported in IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnels.
      </t>
      
      <t>When ISP provides dual stack link to the homenet Edge Router, the Edge Router gets
      	 IPv4 address and performs NAT. The other home routers pick private IPv4 prefixes through HNCP,
      	 and the homenet runs OSPFv2 (<xref target="RFC2328"/>) to configure IPv4 routing.
      	 When ISP provides IPv6-only link and softwire service instead of dual stack,
      	 the same way - private IPv4 prefix  + NAT and build softwire on Edge Router - still works.
      	 However, running OSPFv2 adds additional cost to the homenet. To remove OSPFv2,
      	 building softwire from all home routers is an alternative solution. And it's even
      	 possible to build softwire from end hosts.
      </t>
      
      <t>This document discusses how homenet can build softwires in these methods,
      	 and discusses the compatibility with DS-Lite, MAP and Lightweight 4over6.
      </t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>


    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The document defines the following terms:
      	<list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Edge Router:">A home router that connects to
          	ISP network. ISP can provision stateless DHCPv6 parameters to Edge Routers.
          </t>
          <t hangText="End Router:">A home router that directly connects to
          	end hosts.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Softwire Initiated by Inner Home Router">
    	<t>In this section we discuss how to build IPv4-over-IPv6 Softwire from every inner home router
    		 that connects to end hosts directly, which we call "End Routers".
    		 If a Edge Router that connects to ISP network also connects to some
    		 end hosts, it's also treated as a End Router.
    	</t>
    	
    	<t>To build softwire by End Routers, each router must get the information of the softwire,
    		 including the IPv6 address of remote tunnel endpoint, and other solution-specific information.
    		 All DS-Lite, MAP and Lightweight 4over6 use DHCPv6 option to provision softwire information.
    		 When the Edge Router receives a DHCPv6 response, it advertises the softwire information in DHCPv6 options
    		 to all routers through HNCP. When a inner home router receives the softwire information, it
    		 initiates an IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel. In some solutions (e.g. Lightweight 4over6), the router needs
    		 to get more information before it builds the tunnel.
    	</t>
    	
    	<t>It's possible that the home net connects to multiple ISPs, and each ISP provides its own IPv6 prefix
    		 and softwire configuration to the same or different Edge Routers. In this case, the Edge Router(s)
    		 advertise each Softwire configuration to the homenet independently, and each Softwire configuration
    		 must be bound to the IPv6 prefix from the same ISP. The home routers set up their Softwires accordingly,
    		 and for each tunnel, the tunnel outer IPv6 addresses and inner IPv4 addresses must come the same ISP.
    	</t>
    	
      <section title="Running DS-Lite">
      	<t>In DS-Lite, all routers gets the AFTR-Name option (<xref target="RFC6334"/>) through HNCP.
      		 Each router chooses a private IPv4 prefix for its end users, and does not need to 
      		 advertise the prefix to other routers. The routers build IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel according to the AFTR-Name option,
      		 and routes all IPv4 traffic into the tunnel. The home routes do not perform NAT44.
      	</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Running MAP">
      	<t>In MAP-E, the ISP provides Softwire46 MAP-E Container Option (<xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map-dhcp"/>) to the Edge Router.
      		 Then the whole container option is advertised through HNCP. Each router build MAP tunnel according to the 
      		 option and its Assigned Prefix. The Assigned Prefix is treated as End-user prefix, thus the Delegated Prefix from ISP
      		 needs to be shorter than the expected End-user prefix, e.g. equals to Rule IPv6 prefix.
      		 The Edge Router calculates its public IPv4 address (and PSID) according to the
      		 MAP algorithm. Then the router performs NAT44, and routes all IPv4 traffic into the tunnel. Since all routers
      		 in the homenet shares a single MAP rule, the routers form (possibly part of) a single MAP domain. The ISP
      		 must provide enough IPv4 addresses for the homenet.
      	</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Running Lightweight 4over6">
      	<t>In Lightweight 4over6, the S46 IPv4/IPv6 Address Binding Option(<xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map-dhcp"/>) inside the container option
      		 only contains IPv4 address for a single user.
      		 Thus it can not be used for configuring all home routers. DHCPv4 over DHCPv6 should be used for IPv4 provisioning.
      		 The S46 BR Option(<xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map-dhcp"/>) and 4o6 Server Address Option(<xref target="I-D.ietf-dhc-dhcpv4-over-dhcpv6"/>) are 
      		 received by Edge Router and advertised through HNCP. After obtained the two options, each router initiates DHCPv4 over DHCPv6 queries to get its IPv4 address, and perform
      		 NAT44 on the obtained address. 
      	</t>
      </section>
      
    </section>    

    <section title="Softwire Initiated by Edge Router">
    	<t>IPv4-over-IPv6 Softwire can be initiated by Edge Router directly. ISPs provide their Softwire configuration information to
    		 the Edge Routers, and the Edge Routers build their Softwires directly. After setting up the Softwire successfully,
    		 a Edge Router chooses a private IPv4 prefix and advertise it to the homenet. Edge Routers running DS-Lite do not
    		 perform NAT44, and Edge Routers running MAP and Lightweight 4over6 perform NAT44. Private IPv4 prefix configuration
    		 is through HNCP, and OSPFv2 is used for routing.
    	</t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Softwire Initiated by End Host">
    	<t>Softwire can also be initiated by end hosts. In this case, the Edge Routers advertise the Softwire Configuration information
    		to the homenet as described in Section 3, but the routers do not set up Softwires. The routers need to configure their
    		LAN side local provisioning protocol (e.g. DHCPv6) to provision the Softwire information to end hosts, and end hosts
    		set up the tunnels accordingly.
    	</t>
    	
    	<t>End host needs to support the Softwire mechanisms. Since there could be various types of end hosts, including PCs, tablets or phones,
    		 and devices may run different OSs, it may not be easy to do this.
    	</t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Discussion">
    	<t>In this draft we have discussed three possible scenarios to build IPv4-over-IPv6 Softwire in Homenet.
    		 The purpose of building softwire is to provide legacy IPv4 support for home users, and make it
    		 easier to transit the network to IPv6 and possible to shutdown IPv4.
    	</t>
    	
    	<t>Building Softwire from Edge Router is a native way that is quite close to dual-stack scenario.
    		 However, it requires IPv4 routing inside the home network, and requires IPv4 routing protocol.
    		 Once IPv4 routing is deployed in the home network, it's difficult to shut it down that
    		 even only few end devices require IPv4 service, all home routers need to run IPv4 routing protocol.
    		 It's solved by building softwire from End Routers that IPv4 routing protocol is not required in this case.
    		 Since IPv6 tunnel is built from end routers, there's no IPv4 traffic in the homenet and it could help
    		 the monitoring and network management. IPv4 service can be shut down at each routers, and it will
    		 not affect others routers.
      </t>
      
      <t>Building Softwire form end hosts is possible, but not easy for large scale deployment because user devices
      	are out of ISP's control. In most current home networks, there's already boxes from ISP or third-party. Dealing with
      	routers is much easier for ISP to deploy their network.
      </t>
      
      <t>According to the discussions, this draft recommends IPv6 home network to building IPv4-over-IPv6 Softwire
      	 from every End Routers, to support IPv4 service.
      </t>
    	
<!--
    OSPFv2
    Support in End Host
-->
    	
    </section>
    
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not define a new homenet or softwire mechanism. All the three scenarios are the combination
      	 of current mechanisms: HNCP, OSPF, and Softwire mechanisms: DS-Lite, MAP, and Lightweight 4over6.
      	 Security Considerations in these documents should be considered.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>This document does not include an IANA request.</t>
    </section>

</middle>

<back>

  <references title="Normative References">
    &rfc2119;
    &rfc6333;
    &I-D.ietf-softwire-map;
    &I-D.ietf-softwire-lw4over6;
    &I-D.stenberg-homenet-hncp;
    &rfc6334;
    &I-D.ietf-softwire-map-dhcp;
    &I-D.ietf-dhc-dhcpv4-over-dhcpv6;
  </references>

  <references title="Informative References">
  	&rfc5340;
  	&rfc2328;
  </references>

</back>
</rfc>

